Nice to meet up.
It's fine.
Sound check everything's fine.
OK, OK, so welcome back everyone.
So we are going to finish what we have started seeing yesterday on the out of order execution and
then we would briefly touch up on the data flow and superscalar execution for the, you know, the
course of today's lecture.
And then we are going to move to a different, you know, problem solving skills that raised by modern
high performance processor, which is branch prediction.
It's fascinating topic.
So so yeah, so let's so let's get started.
Wait a SEC, something is not working.
OK, so yeah, so so this is the road map that we are seeing for couple of you know, the last few past
few lectures.
We have started from the single core, single cycle, multi cycle micro architectures.
Then we introduced pipelining.
We introduced you know precise exception support on the pipeline processes.
Yesterday we talked about the out of order execution and then today we are going to finish the out
of order execution, whatever that has left.
We're just going to rejog the memory from yesterday's lecture and then we're going to start with the
branch prediction.
That's the fascinating part of the problem and hopefully I can, you know, convince you that why
that's a problem and then what sort of the solutions that modern architectures impose.
OK.
So again, these are the readings, so I'm not going to go too much into details, but the combining
branch predictor, this is a influential walk and then definitely go through the micro architecture
for superscalar processes paper, paper that also gives you a broader understanding of how
superscalar processes have evolved.
OK, OK, so so so let's wrap it up.
So just to jog your memory, we have seen like these are the four major operations that we need to do
for enabling out of order scheduling or out of order execution in modern high performance
processor.
So we need to link the consumer with the producer so that we saw that we we do it with register
renaming.
Then we want to buffer the instructions that we saw that we can do it with the, you know,
reservation stations.
Then we keep track of the readiness via broadcasting this tag.
Whenever one instruction finishes it's execution.
And then when all the sources of the instruction is ready, then we have a specific logic that wakes
up the instruction and then it can be executed on the and it can be dispatched for execution.
OK, so these are the four broader operations that we have seen.
Again, like these are the like just a in a nutshell.
And so just just to jog this thing, and this is where we would also start with today's lecture is
that what we essentially show for like see in out of order execution is that you still give a
illusion to the programmer that your machine is executing on the von Neumann order, but then
internally you're actually executing in the out of order, which is the data flow.
And now we are going to also take a look at like what happens if you, you know, completely expose
the data flow to the programmer also so that the machine does not even stay in in the von Neumann
model.
So what sort of advantages, what sort of disadvantages that we would see?
That's the we are going to follow also.
So just to jog the memory that the the this data flow graph that this, you know, out of order
machine that internally generates that are also limited by the instruction window.
Instruction window is essentially the reorder buffer size like how many instructions that you have
fetched, but the you have not committed yet, right?
So internally, if you remember that how the the, the, the camel analogy, right?
So you have something on the front that is happening in the in order something on the back that is
also happening in order in somewhere in the middle that that gets garbled up and I'm getting
executed on the out of order mode.
So we have seen this, this, you know, the the.
Simulation yesterday just by looking at and I'm not sure whether some of you or all of you have also
gone through this part that I couldn't cover yesterday but you can you know take a look at previous
lectures so at given at any snapshot like this sort of snapshot of the internals of the reservation
station as well as the registered alias table, you can actually deconstruct the data dependency
graph.
So that's the benefit of, you know, benefit for your understanding also how modern outer photo
processes work.
And it's essentially fascinating to see.
OK.
And then we have also taken a look at, I mean, quickly I have introduced in the last part of to
yesterday's lecture that once you start seeing the out of order processor and then then we also
introduce the reorder buffer at the later end.
So, so that we can have the full picture in our mind that out of order processing with the precise
exception support, right?
So what, what sort of, you know, support that we needed?
We wanted to we showed that, OK, there are two types of register maps.
1 register map would be on the front end register map.
So this is only used for the renaming part.
So that's also speculative like contains, let's say, the valid bits and what sort of tag that you
should be listening to to get the value of that registers.
And then we have also introduced the architectural register map, which is a, let's say, the
checkpointed version of the program.
So if your programs for phase is any exception, if your program needs to be, let's say, stop to
handle some sort of interrupts, then this is where you should be restarting your program from,
right?
So you already have a architectural checkpoint.
So that's the architectural register map.
And we have also seen this graph that I mean seen this picture that OK.
So once we started adding the reorder buffer, then I hopefully motivated that you see value
replications across the board, right?
Like you have value inside the this front end register file, you have the value in the architectural
register map and then you also have values in the reorder buffer.
So I kind of quickly motivated you that OK, instead of storing the full value, you can actually
store A tag.
So the idea is that OK, you're the namespace of the tag won't be as big the, the value what it takes
to store the value.
So you can store 64 bit value that's takes more space than if you just simply store, let's say 12
bits or, you know, 14 bits per the, the, the tags.
So that's what we we did.
And then this is where we left off in the last lecture that you have this now gigantic store of, you
know, values in the same one place, which is the physical register file.
So this is what we call the physical register file and then that kind of, you know, you have the tag
and then the value and then everything else is actually pointing towards this physical register
file, right?
So you the front end register map, each entry is also pointing towards a physical register file.
Similarly, reorder buffer entry is also pointing towards the physical register file and also the
architectural maps.
OK, so this is one of the picture that you know, Pentium 3 and the net burst they they used to have
this.
So we Professor Muthu already discussed about this part in the precise exception lecture, but then
we like after two yesterday's, you know discussion.
So this is what we ended off.
Like you have the front end registered renaming table, you have the back end register aliasing table
and then everything is pointing towards the same register file.
So that is kind of in the middle.
And then you also have the reorder buffer, yes.
Do we have two levels of indirection from from from the register file to the physical file to the
ROP?
No, no, no.
So each, each one has only one level of indirection that points to the physical register file.
So ROP points to the stores the pointers to the physical register file.
Similarly, front end register map also points to the physical register file and architectural
register map also points to the physical register file.
So it's like your value would be stored only one data structure.
I mean think of it as a data structure in hardware.
Your value would be stored in only one place.
Everything else points towards that place.
Instead of storing the values and replicating the values all over the place, you're just storing the
pointers and then that gives you the savings.
OK, any other question at this point?
So this is the independent pro processor that introduced out of order execution for the first time.
And you know this has evolved.
So this is one of the picture of the out of order processor, the like the functional level pictures
of out of order processor from this paper, which is definitely take a look at it and I'm going to,
you know, show you some of the, you know, there are multiple examples.
So this is A21264 processor that that also employs out of order execution.
Then this is a MIPS.
This is something what you are also using for your labs, right?
So this is, you know, one of the first, you know, processes from the MIPS, the generation that also,
you know, tried to keep the hardware as simple as possible, but still.
Succumbed to the out of order processing and I'm adding all the hardware suppose that needed to you
know push the performance.
So that's one of the you know examples IBM power four I'm not going to bore you to depth with all of
this information but then you know these are the processes that you can get a hands on.
So this is aimed at Zen Zen 2.
So people have kind of even though there are not like not all of the information that you are seeing
over here is publicly disclosed by the company itself.
But then people have also reverse engineered these processes to see like what type of, you know, out
of order execution engine that they have in build inside.
So what you can see over here is that, you know, so this is the rename table.
So that that that what you're seeing over here.
So that's a integer rename.
And then this is also the is it working fine?
Yeah.
OK.
So then you also have the floating point, you know, renaming table.
So these are like, think of, you know, internally, this is whatever we have told you on the register
file size.
So they just internally break it down for the non floating point operations and the floating point
operations.
So that's that's, you know, what are the components that you're looking at for the integer
operations on the left hand side, on the floating point operations on the right hand side.
And then you can see the same thing like all of these are the execution units.
So this, you know, so this, this renamer is going to rename the instructions and then put it in the
reorder buffer.
And then this would be dispatched to all the execution units.
So that's the integer execution unit.
And this is the floating point execution unit so that you can see.
So this is one example from AMD and then this is also from Apple.
I mean, you're literally now coming close to the state-of-the-art.
Like what exactly is happening?
And we would go back to this, you know, figures again and again while we complete the superscalar
because that's the last piece of the, let's say, design that we would add.
And that would make you finally arrive at the processor that you're using right now in your phones,
in your laptops.
OK, So what you can see over here is that the entirety of this view order buffer is like gigantic
view order buffer like 6:30.
So let's say, you know, maybe 3-4 years back or maybe five years back, it used to be much smaller.
But now nowadays, and this is also become possible because of multiple reasonings like the Apple
uses a different sort of, you know, ISA.
So that's ARM ISA.
So it's, it's much easier to let's say decode much easier to scale up the system as compared to more
complex ISA like X8664.
So that's why you are obviously seeing over here like 630 instruction reorder buffer, let's say
micro op reorder buffer.
And then then that is backed up by this integer renamer.
So you have different, you know, physical register files.
So this is the PRF that that's what it stands for.
So that's the integer execution unit.
And this is the floating point execution unit.
So, and each renamer is again backed up by different execution, let's say units.
I mean, recall the the pipeline design that we have shown, right?
So different execution unit would have different, let's say latency.
So these are the execution unit that you are seeing.
OK, we would come back to this picture again, like when we would call let's we would go to the Super
scale, which is this 8 wide part.
So we would come back to this picture, but it's just to show you that you know this is exactly
happening what we just taught you on the out of order.
This is exactly happening inside this state-of-the-art processes also.
OK, so now some question that we need to just ponder about before moving into the, the the data flow
part.
Is that why out of order execution is beneficial?
I mean, we have hopefully, you know, motivated towards this answer.
So by now, I guess you can, you know, answer this question that OK, out of order execution is
beneficial because of latency tolerance, right?
So if you have long latency instructions that are supposed to block any dependence from getting
executed, now you have a mechanism that can extract that parallelism, right?
So even if you have some dependence, you can keep it aside and let the independence go on.
Once the dependent instructions would have all of their operands ready, then they can be executed.
So it actually is a latency tolerance mechanism.
So if you have, let's say, long latency operations like floating point operations, memory
operations, then under that circumstances, this is useful, right?
So that obviously brings up one question like what if you're all, you know, instructions take one
cycle?
So that obviously means that there is much less thing to hide, right?
If if every instruction takes one cycle, then obviously the benefit that you can come up from out of
order execution becomes bit lesser.
But life is not that easy.
So we would have the benefits of the out of order execution for quite some time.
Now the another question that we want to ponder is that what if an instruction takes thousands of
cycles, right.
So you may actually think that on on what circumstance instruction would take thousands of cycles?
It's not actually that, you know, uncommon.
I mean, not let's say not thousands, but let's say multi 100 is not that uncommon.
Why?
Because once you start hitting the memory and.
This is the memory wall that we always keep talking about, that if your program is doing some
computations, which is, you know, you know, arithmetic operations, that life is easy.
But the moment you do like you're doing arithmetic operations on something, what is that something?
You're probably fetching the data from memory and then you're computing on that data, right?
So who gives you that data?
So that's the load store operations.
And that actually takes a lot of time.
Now, if you think of easily like if you, if you're executing LLMS, if you're executing any, let's
say, you know, big data applications, like even even even, let's say you know, Google Chrome or
something, right?
So if the, the, the more number of tabs that you're going to open that are also going to create lots
of memory, you know, footprint, right?
And then definitely these memory footprint is, you know, not small enough to be stored inside your
cache.
So that means once your cache hierarchy starts failing and failing, meaning that once your cache
hierarchy starts missing, then you would go to the main memory and and you know, God knows what's
out there and that actually creates a lot of latency.
So then the question is that, OK, what if your instruction takes, let's say multi cycles, even 1000
cycles of latency?
So the first question that we want to answer the how large your instruction window should be to
continue feeding this giant right?
I mean, if you have small instruction window, then you can easily fill it up while you're waiting
for the, you know, long latency operation.
So this is one question that you, you know, you, you, you, I mean that that that can keep you awake
at night.
If once you start designing out of photo processor, like how many of the cycles of the latency,
sorry, how many latency, how big of the latency your out of photo machine can tolerate.
So obviously, you know, the, the, the thing that that limits this scalability of this Thomas
algorithm is the hardware size, right?
So how big is your reorder buffer?
So now you can easily think of it in this way.
Let's say if your reorder buffer is 500 entry, right?
And you can fetch 1 instruction every cycle.
So that means you're literally having a, you know, possibility of 500 cycles to tolerate, right?
And then if you, if you're hitting that wall, if your instruction is taking it's A1 instruction is
taking even more than 500 cycles, you know that there is a problem.
So you would eventually fill up the entire buffer and then you do have no place to go.
And then then your, you know, instruction level parallelism exploitation would start coming to an
halt.
OK, so that's something that you know, it's it's, it's a good thing to analyse.
And then this is how most of the architects, modern architects, they also come up with that, you
know, sizes like, OK, what should be your reorder buffer size, how much your latency you can
tolerate.
And that actually gets dictated by this thing.
The another part that would also dictate that not only just the, you know, size of the reorder
buffer.
So this is what we call the depth of the pipeline, but also the width of the pipeline which we will
come on the superscalar side.
So once we go under the superscalar, you know, part of the lecture and then that would be even more
evident.
OK, so that's to wrap it up.
So what are the advantages of the out of order execution?
So advantages obviously is the latency tolerance, so higher performance in than in order execution.
If you have this sort of mechanisms inbuilt, it also gives you the benefit of exploiting irregular
parallelism, like you're not extracting or you're not asking this from the programmer to specify OK
which instructions can be dynamically executed in parallel.
But your hardware is now capable enough to understand that, OK, these instructions are independent
so I can execute them in parallel.
The dependent instructions would automatically get serialized, right?
So that's what that's what the benefit of out of order execution is that it can dynamically find and
exploit parallel operations in a program.
Like if you think of like pipeline execution, it's some sort of parallelism, right?
So you are over overlapping the latency on, you know, one under the other.
So that's what the parallelism means.
So yeah.
But then there are disadvantages, obviously.
So the one of the disadvantages is the more we add machineries to extract this sort of parallelism,
the more you're making the processor complex and progressively complex, right?
So and that complexity, you know, there is no freelance, right.
So that complexity would also potentially lengthen the critical path delay.
And then that would also dictate, let's say the clock cycle time.
Of the processor like how fast your processor can be clocked like it's 3 gigahertz or is it even
more?
So that's one problem.
And the other problem obviously is that you're you're adding more hardware so now your core is
becoming bigger and bigger, right?
So now, previously, if you, if you could have, let's say like a physical footprint of the core, you
could have, you know, let's say, fit that core inside, I don't know, some X nanometre per square or
X, you know, millimetre square.
Then now it's getting bigger and bigger.
So that's a physical, you know, space that you want.
So just to keep this in mind.
So this is the, you know, the, the, the the equation that we always keep this in mind is that so the
amount of time that your program would take to execute is just the number of this is just a simple.
Let's say mental model for you, right?
So the number of instructions that you have average clocks per instruction that you're going to take
and then the clock cycle time.
So you always need to make sure that you can.
None of these three things are getting hard just to come out winning at the end, right?
So that's what you want to do.
Obviously, if you're not changing the program.
So the number of instructions stays the same.
If you executing the same program for in order processor and out of order processor, what out of
order processor gives you is it would give you the better, you know, average CPI.
So it's basically lowering down your clocks per clocks that you take to execute one instruction.
But at the same time, it may be increasing the clock cycle time.
So just be careful like this, these three things, this is what the Trinity looks like.
So if you want to optimise your, you know, accelerate anything.
So either you need to reduce the number of instructions which compiler can help you or maybe other
other ways that you can help.
You also need to have, let's say lower CPI or if you also need to have lower clock cycles.
So that's what the Trinity is.
And then we're going to come back to this, you know this equation again and again while we go to the
superscalar processor also.
OK, so this is just for from the part of the out of order processing.
But then what I just motivated yesterday on the register site.
But then there is a big part of the problem actually lies in how you can execute load store
instructions out of order.
So we are not going into that.
So if you're interested definitely check out this paper because that's the most, let's say complex
part of today's processor like executing ALU instructions out of order is OK, it's doable.
Load store instructions it's much more harder.
So that's what something we would do any question?
Yeah.
Does this kind of all the border execution always implies pipelining?
Yes, I mean, if you if you don't have pipelining then it defeats it defeats the process from the
very get go, right.
So you probably need, I mean, you definitely need some sort of overlapping that's the pipelining the
first days.
And then you will need the in order or out of order.
But then the the concept that we are going to introduce in the superscalar side that can be actually
useful for both the in order process and out of order process.
So I'll come back to that later.
OK, any other questions?
OK, so if not, so then let's let's take a look at, you know, the some other types of ways to extract
parallelism.
And so this is definitely not out of order processing is one way you can extract instruction level
parallelism, but this is not the only way.
So that's what I'm going to motivate here a bit.
So you have already seen, you know, the parts that we have grayed out, we have already covered this
thing.
So we have started with pipelining.
So that's the first level of, you know, parallelism that you are exploiting.
So just making it one after the other.
Then we have also briefly talked about fine grain multi threading, not me, but in the previous
lectures that instead of doing it, let's say power like parallelism inside a thread, then you can
actually parallelise across the thread, right.
So you would, you know, you would just fetch instructions from different threads and then come back
and then fetch instruction from different threads.
So that's what the final multi threading is.
And then you we have introduced out of order execution.
And then these are the topics that we are going to introduce a bit on let's say a bit high level.
So data flow, you have already seen the part of the data flow in the I sub lecture.
I'm just going to briefly talk about the data flow also.
And so it's essentially just like going to be like the out of order processing, but now you're not
going to be, let's say doing it in a transparent way inside the processor, but you won't you would
give this, you know, page to the programmer also.
So there are good side and the bad side.
So that's what we're going to introduce.
Then there is superscalar execution.
We're also going to introduce and hopefully in next few lectures, we're also going to, you know,
touch up on these other modes of extracting parallelism.
So VLIW so that that's one way SIMD processing, which current GPUs employ a lot.
And then we would also go for systolic adders, which is, you know, Google's TPU.
How many of you know, Google's TPU Any hence?
OK, that's good.
Yeah.
So that that's that explores the different types of, you know, parallelism, which is under the type
of systolic adders.
So we hopefully we are also going to cover this thing in next few lectures.
OK, so so yeah, so, so now, now let's let's go briefly and and and discuss the data flow
architecture.
So just to, you know, recap again, you have already seen how our data flow architecture looks like
it's out of orders, how the exact the execution of out of order for our dispatch machine works,
right?
So out of order ranging dynamically builds this data flow inside the processor and just the limit of
data flow building that you are doing is actually within the instruction window, right.
So that's.
Reorder buffer the number of instructions that you are considering at any point of time.
So that's the window of the instruction that you are creating the data flow graph for right and and
then this is we we already talked about and then this is what the data flow graph.
And as I said, like if you go back and then take a look at the previous lecture, so you can see that
just by looking at this, you know, execution units and then what is happening on the snapshot of a
processor state, you can actually create this data flow graph.
But then so yeah, so, so, so that that's what we discussed that OK, the way that this is getting
executed, that availability of the data, data mines, the order of execution.
So you would just simplify the instruction whenever they're ready and the data node of sorry, a data
flow node fires when it's OK.
So now, now the question is that, so maybe I'm, I'm, let me take a step back.
So what the data, the fundamentals of the data flow is essentially simple like what what you saw in
that out of order execution part that every instruction or if you know the availability of the data
is going to dictate when you can actually fire this instruction, right?
And then when all of your sources are ready, you can simply execute.
And then whatever the program that you're writing now think a bit different from, let's say, your
sequential view of the program.
So whatever program that you are going to write, you would also represent this program in terms of,
let's say, data flow graphs, that, OK, you're going to do this computation, you're going to do this
computation, you're going to do this a bunch of computation.
And then they are connected in this way as you can easily figure out that, OK, you may not be able
to understand, OK, how exactly I'm supposed to write this program.
So that's the exact problem of data flow, let's say architecture.
So if you exploit or if you expose this data flow architecture at the ISA level, so you are
expecting the programmers to even write in this way.
So that's the problem.
So people have done multiple jobs at this data flow architecture at the ISA level multiple times in
the 70s, in the 80s, in the 90s, even some in, in, in, you know, 2000s.
And it's not been that much successful to be honest.
So, so basically what, what, why the, the fundamental reason why this is not successful is the very
reason that if I tell you that, OK, whatever logic that you are thinking in your mind, come up with
a representation using data flow graphs, right?
So it's very hard for you to come up with.
And that's the barrier of entry towards this architecture.
So it's like if you the the life lesson that you can take, and many of you probably would, you know,
create new things in the future.
So probably that life lesson that you can take from here is that if you want to design a different,
let's say, jab at the processing mechanism, right?
So, oh, you come up with, let's say better out of order machinery or what not, right?
So try not to, it would be much easier to, let's say, easily get adopted if you don't put the burden
back to the programmers because that's definitely has a huge barrier of entry.
So if you need a architecture that needs a, let's say, full rethinking of the entire software stack,
like you are expecting too much from programmers and that barely works or very hardly works.
That doesn't mean that it won't work, but history actually tells us that it's, it's really hard to
convince if you need a full blown, you know, rewrite of the programming stack.
But this also tells you that if you can keep the program as is and then you can do that same things
internally, that's going to be extremely successful.
So that's what Intel showed for the out of order execution.
So people are building data flow at the same time, but it's just that data, you know, one one over
the other.
Just because the day out of order execution paradigm does not require the softwares to to be
rewritten or it doesn't burden the programmer to do the same.
So that's the benefit of or that's the, you know, recipe for the success.
So just keep in mind.
And yeah, so that's that's what the out of order execution, that's the prime example.
So try not to disturb as much as possible.
Try not to disturb the entire software stack and then come up with a better hardware architecture,
you would be successful hopefully.
But that being said, like the it's not that completely data flow architectures has not been
exploited.
So people have tried to do this thing in different types of hardware, like for example, Apgs.
They have been very much successful.
Like for example, you know, people have written handwritten kernels to process, let's say, video
encodings.
And then you can easily write this, let's say, specific pro programs using data flow methods.
And you can accelerate these programs in in their PGS.
So if you're designing, let's say, you know, I don't know, like, you know, programs for.
Or financial markets and then there is a huge demand for that to accelerate this programs using a
PGS or anything.
So maybe this would be useful, but for a general purpose computing part data flow is probably not
going to be that much influential.
OK.
So that that hopefully, you know, gives you some sort of understanding what the data flow is.
OK, so this is I'm I'm not going to, you know, go too much into details again.
So this is coming from the, you know, the lecture 9, I guess.
Yeah.
So this is like what sort of, you know, drop trade-offs that you are going.
If you go from like traditional von Neumann, which is a sequential level of execution that requires
a program counter to a data-driven execution, which does not have a program counter, then, you
know, all of a sudden everything starts, you know, going down.
OK, so, so now let's, let's talk about what, what are the different or let's say the, the good part
and the bad part of the data flow architecture.
So the advantages of the data flow as, as I mentioned that they're very good at exploiting irregular
parallelism.
Like if you, and you're also like relying on the, the programmer to expose this parallelism to via
their programme, right?
So you are writing the programme based on, let's say, data flow nodes that OK, these operations
would be together, that operations would be together and that's that.
So they're very good at exploiting irregular parallelism on a real dependence is constrained the
processing, which order that the processing you want to have.
And more often than not, they exploit more parallelism than a traditional von Neumann model.
OK.
But then so this is where the advantages probably ends and advantages are actually good.
It's not that it's bad, but the disadvantages are really huge.
Like for now you're actually trading off the entirety of the precise state semantics.
Like think of it in this way.
If you if your program has multiple data nodes and the only thing that is constraining you from
executing, which you know, instructions, you can execute only by their data dependency.
So you literally don't know any at any point of time if you have to abort the program or let's see
if I have to stop the program and go into handling interrupts, which of the nodes you have already
executed?
Like you have very less, you know, understanding of this precise semantics, right?
So some of the nodes probably have executed, some of the nodes we may not have executed because of
data dependencies and you don't know.
So this is what your von Neumann model provides you, right?
So von Neumann model provides you a sequential view of the program.
So you know that OK, if you want to go from one program to the other, you know, that is the precise
state that we are checkpointing and then we go somewhere else, we come back exactly there.
But now think of like if if conceptually you can think of like a you had dealing with a multi
threaded program at program level without any barriers.
Have you ever programmed this sort of things like multi threaded programs or GPU programming without
any barriers?
You know, this probably something yeah.
So you you start thinking, OK, let's let's accelerate this thing without multi thread and then you
go, OK, I and then, you know, your log becomes completely nonsense, right.
So it gets out of order.
So that's what we are dealing with.
So at at any point of time if you want to go back and say that OK, I want to move from this program
and then come back again, you don't know like which which thread has been executed at what level
that we have has been executed.
So you need some sort of a barrier and then you can easily backtrack what exactly was happening.
So that's exactly what we are looking at.
So if you get rid of these, you know, constraint that OK, there is no sequential semantics.
It's very hard for us human minds or even program like computer itself to come up with a precise
state semantics.
So that's one thing.
The second thing is like any any and obviously the hardware over it is huge.
In many cases you might actually also deal with too much of parallelism like you're literally waking
up or I won't say the word waking up.
You can literally like just because of this, you know, data dependency firing principle, you at any
single cycle, you may actually have a lots of numbers of instruction to be, you know, ready for
execution.
Then your life becomes harder that OK, out of all of these ready instructions, which one you want to
schedule, which one you want?
Not like we just want to de prioritise, right, Because the decision that you are going to make
eventually going to be important, OK, You prioritise one over the other that actually, you know,
like propagated a lot for the end to end execution, right.
So that becomes much more harder.
And then there are other, you know, topic problems like how to enable mutable data structure.
This is exactly what I was telling you about multi threaded, you know, programs, you write multi
threaded programs without any locks or semantics and try writing and reading the one data
structure.
You know what exactly that brings.
So that's what we are mentioning over here.
OK.
So hopefully I can, you know, convince you that there are good sides of data flow architecture, like
if you want to build a data flow architecture at the ISA level like.
You want to give this power to the programmers, but then it's very hard for the programmer.
I mean, average programmer is not that.
Let's say I once should, I should not use the word, but average, if you put the board into the
programmers, it barely walks because they're not that much, let's say, willing to put that effort.
So most of the party needs to be, or better needs to be done at the hardware level itself.
OK, so, so yeah, so there are multiple other, let's say, lectures and readings that you can cover.
And I'm not going to cover too much into detail.
So that's what the data flow architecture is.
And then Professor Moody used to cover this data flow architectures much more detail in previous
lectures.
So I'm have put all the, you know, links over there.
And that kind of brings me to the last part of this.
You know, this phase of the lecture is which is a super scalar execution.
And that's the last piece of the puzzle before we jump into some other types of techniques.
And then this would actually make your pipeline or the processor design exactly what you're using
right now.
That's the last piece of the puzzle.
Superscalar.
OK, so as the name suggests, what the superscalar execution is, the idea is that till now, whatever
you have seen is that if you if you recall that you know, data flow graph or not the data flow
graph, if you recall the pipeline, you're still doing 1 fetch at a time, 1 decode at a time and
then multiple executes, right?
What if we can increase that width So we can let's say fetch 2 instructions at a time, decode 2
instructions at a time.
Similarly, we can execute many things that that's the data flow order and then we can also let's say
commit 2 instructions at a time.
So that's what superscaler is going to do.
So the idea is that you you fetch, decode, execute, retire multiple instructions per cycle.
OK, so that's you know the key idea.
So if you if you have N wide superscalar processor and typically today's processor are like let's
say 6 to 8 wide, it can go even bigger than that in some cases.
But in, in, in on average, let's say it's, it's 8 wide processor that we are looking at at, at this
point today.
So in wide superscalar processor essentially means that you have the capability to fetch any
instructions, decode any instructions, rename any instructions, commit any instructions at a cycle.
So that's the power that we have bet now obviously nothing is free lunch.
You need to add hardware resources for doing so.
And now the the thing that you need to keep in mind that you need a data dependency mechanism to
also figure out the dependency between that group of instruction that you're fetching together.
So if if you in your mental model, think of it in this way.
So right now we are doing it on the like right now we are doing the data dependency search or data
dependency tracking at the horizontal scale.
Like you have different pipeline stages and then then you're executing another instructions
overlapping and then you have the dependency analysis in the horizontal scale.
But now you're instead of having one instruction going in like this, you have a bunch of instruction
going in one cycle.
So you're just making the, you know, BLOB a bit bigger and then that goes in this way.
So you not only need to, let's say detect the dependency on the horizontal scale, but you also need
to detect the dependency on the vertical scale, right.
So that's the, you know, the group of instructions that you're going to fetch, the group of
instruction that you're going to decode, you need to understand, OK, is there any data dependency
between those instructions?
OK, So that's what you know, that was makes actually this hardware a much more complicated and that
also makes the the this end to be limited.
Like in a real world.
You can also go for let's say 16 wide out of like super scaler.
That's not what we can afford to do, let's say one cycle.
So that's the what the problem is.
And if you recall that, that, you know, if you recall that the the, the, the equation, if you go for
one design decision that increases your weight, but at that comes at a cost of lower frequency or
lower, you know, cycle or a longer cycle length, then you are again losing in the end.
So we don't need to or do we don't want to do that.
OK, Now this is one thing that many people often, let's say, confuse a bit.
So when we talk about superscalar, we typically tend to think that oh, superscalar is a concept that
can only be applied on top of let's say out of order process.
Absolutely not.
And this is one thing that that paper that we are talking about, you know, is so he's, you know,
Seminole walk that also makes this a bit, you know, wrong assumptions that it's a modern out of
super scaler processes design, but it's actually internally discusses both like super scaler as
well as, you know, out of auto processor.
So what do I mean by this thing?
So this is the Cartesian, you know, design choice that you are actually looking at.
So your processor internally can have out of order dispatch in order dispatch.
And for both of those design point, you can literally come up with both scalar processor and.
Super scalar processor.
So scalar processor like you can literally have in order scalar in order super scalar.
Traditionally out of order scalar has not been developed because of the you know, the the way that
design has been progressed historically.
And then then we have out of order super scalar processor actually in in design wise Intel, I think
alpha also, they have both gone from in order super scalar try to push the boundary there.
And then they have introduced out of out of order scalar.
And then they have finally gone to out of sorry, out of order superscalar.
So that's the, you know, natural progression that we had looking at.
OK, but keep this in mind that scalar or superscalar processing is not a concept that is completely
tied up to the out of order processing.
OK, OK, so here is an example of what the out of order, you know, scalar superscalar process looks
like.
So as you can see over there and, and what, what I'm showing here is that instead of having one
instruction getting through the pipeline and then this is 1 simple example, because of the in order
pipeline, you have multiple instructions.
So I'm, I'm showing over here like you, you are getting 2 instructions at a time.
You are also looking up to the register file with two instructions, all of them, you know their
register opponents.
You're also going, let's say 2 instructions worth of data paths to the AL use and you're doing like
basically you're replicating everything for accommodating 2 instructions at a time.
So you can easily understand what is the, you know, the hardware over it that you can introduce over
here.
So the idea is that, you know, if you if you just replicate, your IPC becomes double, right?
I mean, that's easy peasy.
But then you also need to make the dependencies inside that 2 instructions that you're going to
fetch.
So I'm going to just show you someone example over here.
So, so see this is 1, you know the program and if we design let's say 2 wide super like in order,
sorry, SO2 wide in order for pipeline.
So we would expect the ideal IPC to be two.
And then this is what it's happening, right?
So look, if you look into this, like these two instructions, they're completely independent with
each other.
These two instructions again, they're independent with each other.
These two instructions are also there the same thing.
So what we are doing, we are essentially fetching 2 instructions together, decoding and it is
flowing through the pipeline while the second group of two instructions are going through the
pipeline, right.
So this is what you know if if you go on this part, you will actually see that OK, this entire 6
instructions will be fetched in three cycles.
So that would give you IPC of two.
Life is good, right?
But now if you, if I just change the programme a bit, now what is happening over here?
So you can see that if you want to fetch these two instructions together, they have a data
dependency.
So obviously you cannot have dependencies between these two.
If you want to execute the only way that you can execute OK, the first instruction that you can have
like the group of two that becomes empty.
So that's your empty slot because you can't, you can't literally execute this second instructions
together.
So what you need to do then you're scheduling, you know, the, the grouping goes a bit, you know,
haywire.
So now these two instructions will come together.
These two instructions becomes together.
And then this one.
Now, if I ask you a simple, so obviously if you, if you do this now all of the instructions are
getting fair, you know, issued in five cycles.
So you can see your IPC dropped from 2 to 1.2.
So that's the problem.
Now if I ask you a simple question, So what you can do to make this IPC come back up to two anyone?
Yes.
I mean we are already doing the data forwarding as much as we can.
So, so here we are forwarding, here we are forwarding.
So yeah, I mean we are we are our in order pipeline is still going strong.
Yes, yes.
But let's say if we want to stay with this design constraint, we can fetch only two.
So this is A2 wide super scaler with this design.
What else can you do?
Yes.
OK, but this is a true dependence, right?
So it doesn't matter if you, even if you have, you know, infinite registers, this is your program
and then the ad is literally dependent on loads.
So you can't get rid of that.
But there is maybe a different way.
Think, OK, I'll come back to you again.
Yes, which way we want to reorder?
Uh huh.
Makes sense.
I mean, if you if you have more registers then just don't use this T 0 here and then use a different
register and then probably just replace.
But the core idea is is exactly what what you wanted Sir.
Even in with this sequence of program, even with this set of architectural registers, if you just
Simply put this or and replace the OR with the add program like syntactically the program would
stay exactly same you, you would get the final same exact output, but you would have the IPC come
back up to two because see this or is only going to be dependent on this store What?
So if you replace this or with the AD, you're still obeying all the dependencies that you have.
It's just that you have restructured the code of bit and now your superscalar processor can execute
it with with, you know, 2 IPC.
So that's basically what I'm trying to tell you here is that if compilers are in, you know,
knowledgeable that, OK, it can reorder the instructions at compile time while obeying the
correctness of the program, you can get, you know, extract better benefits out of it.
So that's what also happens in in today's, you know, compilers.
So they they try to do, you know, all sorts of reasoning to handle the data dependences.
OK.
So I'm not going to go into the full details of this, that there are multiple ways of handling the
data flow.
We have, you know, solve all of these things like, you know, bypassing, waiting, eliminate,
eliminating the, you know, the, the, the, the data dependence at the software level.
So this is exactly what we discussed.
Like if you reorder, if your compiler can reorder instructions while obeying all the, you know,
correctness, you can handle this thing.
And all of this can be applied at superscalar process level.
OK.
So this just quickly go through before you know taking the break that So what we are the advantages
that we are looking at the superscalar execution is that obviously it would provide you the higher
instruction throughput, right.
I mean, I mean if you if you go 4 wide you were committing also 4 white.
I mean yeah, I mean that's no brainer, right.
So higher instruction throughput and then just just keep this in mind.
So if, if you have, let's say, higher instruction throughput essentially means that your CPI is
dropping now.
So overall, you know, the execution time of the program is also dropping.
But keep this in mind also that you don't want to operate at a level where you're just chasing the,
you know, dropping the CPI so much.
Now your cycle is also becoming larger.
So if you are operating and let's say instead of 3.2 gigahertz, if you're operating at 2 gigahertz,
you better compensate that with the, you know, the, the betterment of that you are doing inside the
hardware.
Otherwise you're eventually going to lose in in the end because that the wall clock time is not
going to, you know, go any different.
So the disadvantages and then that's what the, the type or the constraints that you need to keep in
mind while, you know, implementing these things in the hardware because that all the disadvantages
is going to or potentially going to increase the clock cycle time is at a higher complexity.
Now, if you go for, let's say, you know, 2 wide superscalar, 8 wide superscalar, now you need to add
so many circuitry to even detect the data dependency within that group that actually adds latency.
I mean, hopefully the I mean, in worst case, it can also significantly lengthen the clocks clock
time.
So that's what I'm showing over here.
It requires A dependency checking between the concurrent executions register renaming, which is the
current, you know, the bottleneck in today's out of order processor.
Like it becomes extremely complex to obey all of all of those dependencies within the, you know,
fetch group and then still renaming it correctly.
So that that thing that becomes much more complex.
And then, as I said, like this can all of this can actually indirectly affect your clock cycle time
and you don't want to go there to which eventually, you know, disrupts this final the the the
equation that we see.
And obviously it needs more hardware resources.
So that's I'll just, you know, close it with, with this part of the lecture, with this example.
So Intel Pentium is the first in order superscalar processor.
And then that actually came before the Pentium Pro and Pentium Pro actually introduced the out of
order part.
So think of it in this way.
So Intel 4 to 6, I think that that that's the first processor that Intel built with introduced
pipeline.
Then you have Intel Pentium, it was supposed to be called Intel 5 to 6, but then you know, somebody
came up with this for marketing term.
So that's Intel Pentium for you.
And then Intel Pentium introduce a superscalar in order pipeline.
Then you have Intel Pentium Pro, which is the out of order superscalar pipeline.
And this is the same thing that was going on for on from the alpha side also.
So A21, so 21164 is the first processor that introduced, I mean not first person like from first
person in the alpha side that introduced in order superscalar and then 21264 introduced out of
order.
Then this is the in out of order from Intel Pentium side our Alpha 21264.
Is out of order super scalar from alpha side.
And then yeah, for some reason alpha also went out of the market.
It will stay back and that's what you're seeing over today.
OK, so that's that's you know, and now all over the course of that generation, like since 2002, what
we are now to 2026, this is what we are actually seeing.
Like we have kept increasing the width of the pipeline, which is the Super scalar width.
And we have also kept the number of entries that we can hold in the pipeline, which is the depth of
the pipeline, the reorder buffer significantly.
And then that kept on, you know, providing performance benefits over the generations across.
So yeah, so, so this is again like I'm revisiting this figure again.
So as you can see over here that that's, I don't know whether you can see this.
Yeah.
So this is 4 instructions per cycle.
So this is coming from AMD Zen 2.
So that's the width of the Super scaler.
And if you go to Apple's M1 that actually clocks at 8, you know, wide decode.
So that's basically the superscalar width of your M1 processors.
I think map will still clocks at somewhere around 8 or 10 wide decode.
Bubbles meaning that you, you, you cannot commit those instructions at a group also.
So always keep this in mind that you would fetch in order, you would commit in order.
So if you can't commit, so let's say you have a width of, let's say 4.
So you can fetch 4, you can decode 4.
Then out of order becomes, you know, the entire out of order part.
And then everything gets populated in the reorder buffer, right?
So you're committing something from the reorder buffer exactly on, you know, 4 by 4.
So every cycle you are committing 4.
So now you would scan the reorder buffer from the oldest instruction to the youngest instruction.
You would say that OK, I would start committing the four cycle, I would start committing 4
instructions.
If I stop somewhere the remaining instructions at that second, even if you have space to commit, you
cannot commit.
So you would just commit 2 or let's say 1 and that's that.
So that actually drops the IPC significantly.
So even if we have the support for let's say 8 wide commit or 8 wide, you know, commit processor,
you may actually frequently see your process is not committing 8 instructions per cycle.
It would be very, you know, likely that you or it would very hard to see when you know anything
close to even 8 make sense.
OK, if you don't have any other question, then I think we would again like have some break and then
then let's meet at 3:15.
And then we would start with the second part of the lecture, which is branch prediction.
Everything is fine.
This is getting broadcasted.
OK, OK, so, so now we are going to take a look at other part of the lecture and this is something
that is really fascinating and I hope that I do a good job to you know make you also fascinated
about this problem.
And this is one of the quintessential puzzle to enable what we have built in now.
So out of order superscalar pipeline everything is fine or even simple pipeline is fine.
But then we have kind of briefly talked about this problem which is the branch prediction problem.
But branch prediction basically says that OK, what needs to be executed next?
One of your fellow classmate, he has asked the question that, OK, is there any reason why let's say
Apple or ARM can execute these many instructions make it, you know, wider superscaler as compared
to let's say X86 counterpart.
So one of the answer would be lying on on this, you know, top part of the lecture.
OK.
So, so yeah, so that's what the wait a SEC laser pointer is the pointer.
Yeah.
So on the grand scheme of things.
So this is what we are going to look at.
So again, so this is the last part of the piece of the puzzle to enable literally to enable what we
have built in now or the out of order superscalar which is the branch prediction.
So what we are going to deal with is the control dependence.
I think we have seen this control dependence in the ISA lectures if I am not mistaken.
But just to jog your memory, So what control dependence means that once you start designing A
pipeline processor, right?
So every cycle you are fetching next instruction, next instruction, next instruction.
What exactly is the next instruction?
So that's if you if you start going to the details, then you would see the OK, the devils are in the
details.
So what should we fetch from Indiana?
The next instruction, I mean next cycle.
So obviously the address is.
So the answer is the address of the next instruction.
But what is the next instruction?
So if you have a sequential piece of code that, oh, you're just writing, oh, I'm going to do this.
I'm like, I'm loading a value from array A and I'm adding something from array.
I'm storing something from array.
Life is good, but you are not only writing those that sort of code you have if else clause you have
fall loop, you have do while loop, you have while loop.
So these are like branch instructions, right.
So you keep on doing something.
If some condition is not met, you would go back or you would go you know if if let us say on some if
condition is met, then you go somewhere else.
If the if it is not made, then you would do the some other things.
So how exactly you would get to know that what is the address of the next instruction?
That is actually a bit problematic.
So if the instructions are so that's what we call the control dependence.
So you have seen the data dependence part.
So data dependence meaning that one instruction cannot be executed till its source operands are
ready.
So that's the data dependence.
So you cannot execute.
The other fundamental form of dependence is the control dependence, meaning that this instruction
you like where exactly you whether you would execute this instruction or not, it depends on some
let's say branch conditions, right?
And that's the control dependence.
So that is what we are going to look into this this this part of the lecture.
OK, so now the, the the question is that if you have, let us say non control for flow instruction,
like if you just have a sequential piece of code, then your next PC calculation is much simpler.
Now the question is what would be the next PC?
So that actually lies in in this condition.
So in case of ARM, in case of of probably risk 5 also.
So ARM ISA for sure is your instruction is going to be.
So what?
What would be your next instruction if you don't have any conditional branch If then your next
instruction would be whatever is your current instruction plus some instruction length, right?
Whether the size of the current instruction.
Now for ARM, the size of the current instruction is always fixed.
So you know if you are sequential then you always get to go from PC equals PC +4.
So it is like 4 bytes ahead.
Now for X86 ISA, that thing is not fixed.
So your X86 instruction can vary somewhere between you know like I think 2 bytes.
I am, I am probably mistaking here, but it can go as big as let's say 16 bytes, 17 bytes.
So that creates the problem that OK, if you know that OK, this instruction, what would be the next
in?
Well, like this instruction size, you don't even know the size because size would be only known at
the decode phase, like how big is that instruction, right?
So and then by the time you went to the decode phase, you already you know you're supposed to fetch
the next instruction, right?
So if you don't know the size and you don't know like what suppose you are supposed to fetch.
So you can easily see that.
Even like in complex ISR.
So this is one thing that also complicates the process.
So if you if you know that OK your every instruction is of fixed width, then you know that you you
can also say that OK, this part of the encoding is giving me the OP code.
This part is the source registers.
This part is what not right?
But if you make it variable, then life becomes harder.
So your decoder becomes harder to do and your pipeline also becomes harder to even keep feeding what
what exactly is going on?
So this is one of the reason why let's say risk based Isas like ARM can actually build much more,
let's say wider pipeline because you're, you know, many part of the decode logic, many part of the
fetch logic becomes much more easier as compared to X86.
Now you might actually question this, why then X86 even go into this direction?
So the answer lies in the fact that if you go for, let's say, you know, complex instruction, and
that's the age-old debate and I'm not going too much into details over there.
But if you go for complex instruction set ISA, then you can also represent the program much more
compact view.
Like you can literally cramp the program down.
Like you can have like 1 instruction that's going to do lots of things.
Like you can literally load 2 operands from memory and then do the addition and then store it in the
memory 1 instruction.
But if you want to do this thing in ARM, you literally need two different loads, then another AD and
then another store.
So instead of having 4 instructions, you can actually represent one instruction.
So that's, you know, COM makes the program compact.
And then that was some, let's say, legacy reasons why we went for, you know, CIS kind of ISA.
But hopefully I kind of motivated you that even like in complex ISA even identifying next PC, even
if you have a sequential logic that is also become may become problematic.
And if you have control logic, then you know, good luck.
So that is I am going to, you know, motivate over here.
So as I said, like easy to determine if you know the size of the face instruction, life becomes easy
if your size is, you know, constant or if it is a fixed size.
But then it becomes much more harder if you do not have the fixed size instruction.
OK, now it becomes much more problematic if you face a control flow instruction like let's say a
conditional branch, right?
Like, oh, if this is the condition, then you are going to do something.
Then how exactly would know that, OK, it's going to be like if it's true or false, like what exactly
we are going to do is like, oh, if this register contains a value X and that only going to happen
when you go to that execution phase, right?
Like then you will actually go to the comparators and then comparators would going to tell you that
OK, this is the output of this function that would depend, you know, dictate what whether you are
going to take the branch or not taking the branch.
So that's what you know, makes it even harder if you have a control flow branch.
The next PCE identification goes completely here and that's what we are going to gradually build up
on this part of the lecture and you know, next week's lecture is that what we have done in the
literature to make sure that you would always keep feeding the pipeline with as much correct work
as possible and as much in the correct direction as possible.
So that's what we are going to look into it.
OK, so before going too much into like first into the, you know, the branch prediction part.
So let's let's revise the basics first.
So we have different types of branch in the programme, right?
So I am going to give example.
So conditional branch is essentially the E fails clause that you write or maybe let's say you know
the while loop, do while loop everything.
So you have a condition.
So the direction whether you are going to take it or not, that's not not known at runtime, sorry, at
fetch time because it would only be known once you execute that.
And the number of possible targets are two, either you take it or not take it, right.
So that's easy now, but then you have unconditional branches like, you know, it's just always taking
branches, right?
You just jump to somewhere like when you when you let's say not function call, but let's say when
you're going to some part of the code, like you just simply have the jump instruction.
So that's going to be, you know, always taken.
And you know what is the the number of possible address is going to be only one.
But this is also going to be known to you at the decode phase because this address where you are
supposed to jump, that's embedded inside the bytes that you fetch just now.
But you don't know what that is once you go to the decode stage.
And I'm going to show you like that creates a problem.
Then you have the call.
This is just a simple function calls.
Obviously, it is always going to be taken.
There is only one possibility where you can go.
So that's the number of possible phase address.
Then you have return which is again like always taken, but it can be different types of written
addresses, right?
So if you let's say, call function A, then you're going to.
Function A calls B, then when B returns then you would come back to A.
But then if let's say B calls C and then when that C returns and you come back to B.
But you can easily say thing, I mean easily see that OK, if you keep track of who calls, then you
can also easily predict, OK, where to return because it's a stack kind of thing, right?
So whenever you call, you put it, put it on top, put it on top.
And whenever, when you are returning, so you are basically just popping it so you know exactly where
to return.
So that's also a bit easy to let's say predict where should I go.
But then the, the most critical part that is very hard to deal with is the conditional branches and
the indirect branches.
So that's the first and the last.
So conditional branches is hard to you know, deal because we do not know whether it is going to be
taken or not.
So that is the problem.
And the indirect branches are actually problematic because even though their direction is always
taken, but you can go literally multiple places like when you have when you write let us say switch
cases.
So switch there is a variable and then you have multiple switch cases.
So that is actually a indirect branch.
So what exactly it happens is that you jump to a register, whatever the value of the register is at
runtime, you literally jump over there and there is multiple things can be stored in the register
and you don't know unless you actually execute that program.
So that's what the indirect branches are.
So most of the machinery that that we invest in the processor is actually, you know, focused on this
two types, conditional and indirect branches.
OK, OK, so now, OK, so, so, so the, the problem that I hopefully I have all already kind of
motivated is that how to handle the control dependence is basically it's critical for us to keep
the pipeline full with correct sequence of dynamic instructions.
And there are multiple potential solution.
And I'm hopefully going to give you more motivation why this is so important to keep the pipeline
full with correct instructions because if you go on the wrong thing, whatever that you are going to
execute is probably going to be meaningless because you don't want to go on that part.
So think of it as assembly line.
If you have some sort of, you know, even that going to stop the assembly line, then you still need
to keep the assembly line fed with some, you know, predictions.
And that's what we are going to do so that you better be right at what you're predicting.
Otherwise, if you later on figure out that you went to a different wrong direction, everything that
you did till now is going to be flushed and then one slide would be I hope that that's going to
convince you why this is so important.
OK, So what are the potential solutions?
Obviously you just simply stall the entire assembly line, right?
You don't know what to do.
You fetch any instruction.
You don't know what is the next instruction going to be.
You stall the pipeline and I hope, you know, I am going to show like why that's not a good, you
know, solution.
Then the next solution is guess the next, you know, fetch address in computer architecture, if you
come up with any problem, the first set of thinking you should be can I predict this?
And that that's something that, you know, keep in mind, like if you if you come up with a problem
that OK, this is becoming, you know, data dependent or this is becoming something that's hard to,
you know, understand, let's just predict it.
Let's see.
So that's what we are going to do that OK, what is the next address?
You have a problem of understanding the next address, let's predict it.
So that's what the branch prediction is.
Then there is another, you know, way of dealing branch delay slot, which probably have seen a bit.
I am going to, you know, motivate a bit more over here.
Fine grain multi threading.
We have always seen this thing.
So it's basically just, you know, ignoring the entirety of the problem all together.
We are saying, oh, I fetch this, fetch this, fetch this, fetch this and then I decode this, decode
this, decode this.
So that's anyway going to give you some sort of head room if you have multiple threads.
But that give know this that it's not going to.
If your single thread performance is critical to you, final multi threading is not going to help you
that much.
If anything final multi threading is going to make your single threaded performance even go bad
because you are literally switching from one.
Like instead of you know, switching N instructions for that thread, you are actually switching.
Let us say you know, north instructions, sorry, one instruction every N cycles, right?
So that is what fine grain multi training does.
But if you do care about, let us say the performance as a whole, which you know GPU's commonly
employ that you have lots of threads going on, then fine grain multi training can help you in that
aspect.
OK.
And then there are other solutions like oh, you can eliminate the control flow instructions all
together.
So that is what we call the predicated execution.
And another problem is or another way of dealing with the problem is you don't know what exactly is
going to happen and let's execute both the parts.
Can someone say that what can be a problematic for the last solution?
Yes.
That's true, but there there might be a bigger problem over here.
Anyone.
It's actually easy to see if you have a branch, let's say you have two possible outcomes and then
you are all I'm, I'm making a, you know, assumption that OK, let's let's execute from both the
outcomes you encounter another branch and another branch.
It just keeps on expanding.
You know, the exponential space, right?
So how you can easily see that OK, if some branch is not resolved and then you found out another
branch that also again went to two.
So if you go let's say 5 unresolved branch and each branch can have two possibilities, you are
literally dealing with, you know, 32 possibilities at once and that's too much.
So the multipath execution in some cases, you know, it may be a solution, but it's definitely too
much hardware intensive.
So all that, you know, the mostly what what we are going to see is that the branch prediction as
the, you know, dominant solution to address this problem.
OK, so now let's let's start with, you know, understanding each of these bit more the, let's say,
convince like to to convince you that why the other solutions are not that great of, you know,
solution.
So the first thing that you can obviously do is solve the pipeline, right?
So let's see what happens.
So, so when you fetch this instruction, let's say you you fetch this instruction at you know T is 0
at this point you do not know what is the Yeah.
So, so if you face this instruction at T0, at this point, you do not know first of all that whether
it is a branch instruction or not because that is only going to be known at the decode phase.
And you also do not know like what is the size of the instruction?
What exactly you are going to go in the next cycle.
So even if you have a, let's say, you know, regular piece of code without having any branches, that
would still give you, you know, problems, right?
So you cannot fetch in this cycle.
And only if you have, you know, decoded and you understood that, oh, this is a branch and probably
this is what were the address that I, I'm sure I should be going that when you, you can actually
fetch an exchange instruction.
So that creates this bubble.
Right, so that if you go on and keep on doing this so it you can easily see that OK, everyone like
your, your IPC immediately gets halved, right?
So now one bubble you can see every, you know, cycles, right?
So that kind of makes, you know, hopefully that convinces you that OK, you know, having the stalls,
I mean stall until you know, the next one PC is not a good idea right now.
What are the other things fine grained multi threading I have already discussed.
So let's not go over, you know, the details into this.
And then the the the this piece of the puzzle is the the the branch prediction.
Now let me so this is a slide that, you know, I hope that it's going to be it should objectively
motivate you why branch prediction is needed.
So to to give a, you know, thought calculation.
Let's, so let's consider this thing.
So control flow instructions are too frequent in the code that we normally write.
So 15 to 25% of all the instructions.
I mean in general, just a rule of thumb, every 5 instructions that you are going to execute is
probably going to be branch.
So keep that in mind.
OK, So the question is that OK, next page address after the control flow instruction is not
determined after the North cycles in a pipeline process N cycles meaning that if you have let us
say from fetch to execute, if you have N number of you know, pipeline stages, definitely you need
to wait before you know what is the outcome of this branch, right?
For sure.
Is that correct?
So from the fetch to where you know execute.
Now, if you think of it in this way, oh, if this branch is also dependent on some other instruction,
let's say it's a memory instruction, that is this branch is going to depend on South.
What what do you mean by this?
You have probably written code like this.
Oh, if a of I, the array of you know, I is 0, then you do things.
What exactly internally does it do?
A of I is essentially a load instruction.
So that loads some piece of data from the memory to the register file.
And then then you are just simply checking whether this register value is 0 or not.
So your branch instruction is actually dependent on a memory instruction.
Now memory instruction can take even like many cycles.
So that also longest like how you know how much far from you fix the branch and when the branch is
going to be resolved, right.
So what I am saying is that even if you don't have any data dependence, it's like let's say you do
know what is going to be like.
All the operands of this branch instruction is known at that point.
Still you have to wait for this N cycles between the fetch and the execute stage.
You don't know what's going on between that.
Now if you have a wide superscalar processor, keep this in mind.
If you have W wide processor, you can literally fetch W instructions in one cycle.
Decode double instructions in one cycle and then by, you know, rename double instructions in one
cycle and so on and so forth, right.
So what we are looking at here that if you let us say if you have to wait for this N instructions
and you are saying that oh you know what, I am going to just predict something.
So what is the cost of prediction?
So you are literally by the time you would know what is the actual outcome of this branch, you would
have actually fetched N into West instructions.
Is that clear?
So, you know, you would get to know the output outcome of the branch at after N cycles.
And by that time you have already fetched and those instructions are keep flowing through the
pipeline N into West instructions.
Right now you can easily see like the the more you would increase the width of the pipeline.
It also it's a big gamble.
So you are executing more if your branch predictor is not working, you're also, you know, losing
more.
So this is the reason why your branch, you know, the branch prediction needs to be very, very
accurate.
And this is a slide that I'm, I'm going to, you know, show.
So let's for the sake of this discussion, let's say n = 20.
I mean 20 pipeline stages.
I mean, this is a, you know, very good assumption.
And in modern processor, it's the number of pipeline stages is even higher than this.
So let's say, you know, this is 20 pipeline stages and we have, let's say 5 wide superscalar fetch.
You already saw that, you know, AMD is operating somewhere around 6, but you know, but Apple is
operating somewhere even more than six, right?
So, so 5 is a, you know, decent assumption over here.
And, and also, you know, we are using this to keep the calculation easy.
So we are also assuming that everyone out of five instruction is a branch.
This is also not a bad assumption to make because that's what have been empirically studied over the
time that whatever code that we write, it has one out of five instructions as a branch.
And and then we also OK, so this is the assumption every five instruction block ends with a branch.
And then the question if I ask you that how long does it take to fetch 500 instructions?
So let us let us try to solve this thing, right.
So if you have 100% accuracy of the branch, so that means sorry, the 100% accuracy of the branch
predictor.
If you have that, then you are fetching 500 instructions.
You have the capability of fetching 5 instructions per cycle.
So answer is obvious 100 cycles you would need to fetch 500 instructions correct?
That is you know easy peasy.
Did you waste anything answer is not so you have 100% accurate every cycle whatever you fetch it is
actually on the correct thing.
Life is good right?
So you no wasted work.
Your IPC is 500.
The the number of you know cycles that you I mean this is the fetch IPC.
This is obviously not the commit IPC.
So thing in that fetch let us say the fetch IPC is you are fetching 500 instructions in 100 cycles.
So your IPC is 5, exactly the way that you have designed your processor.
But life is not that good.
So now let's say if you have 99% accuracy of branch predictor, what happens?
99% is much more higher than what your random prediction can do.
I mean, it's, it's actually almost behaving like an Oracle, right?
So you can easily imagine.
So if you have 99% accuracy, what what is happening?
So 100 of the cycle, like 100 cycles, obviously you need to fetch 500 instructions in the end,
right?
So you are no, you are not going anywhere from the 100 cycles for sure.
So that's that's, you know, 100 cycles that you have spent on the correct path, but then you're also
spending 20 cycles on the wrong path.
Why?
Because out of 100, you know branches, let's say 1 branch, you have mispredicted that one branch
actually took 20 cycles to finish.
And that 20 cycles, whatever you did in that 20 cycle is wasted.
So that's the 20 cycles that you have spent on the wrong path, right?
So the overall number of cycles that you are seeing is 120 cycles.
Now if you look into how many instructions that you have fetched those 20 cycles that you have, that
single branch got mispredicted out of 100 branches that you have, you actually went to something.
And since you are, you know, superscalar process, you have designed a superscalar process, you know,
you know, to to push the performance you have for that entirety of the 20 cycles.
You have also fetched like 5 instructions every cycle, right?
So that means you have, you know, instead of fetching, let us say only 100, sorry, instead of
fetching only 500 instructions, you have also fetched 20 into 5.
So that is 100 instructions more, right?
So that's, that's what the 20% extra instruction that you fetch.
So instead of fetching 600 like 500 instructions, you have now actually fetched 600 instructions.
So keep that in mind.
But now if you look into the correct IPC, because that's what it matters.
Like, I mean, I don't, I don't give the goodie points to the processor because it fits something,
you know, it did a good job or fetched at least something on the wrong path.
That's not how we measure.
So if you measure the correct path, fetch IPC which is the final, you know, IPC that we care about
for you.
The program, what did we see?
So you have fetched 500 instructions correctly because that's the programme is and we actually took
120 cycles.
So that already dropped your.
So this is what?
So this is like 4 IPC, right?
So you already dropped from you know 5 IPC to four IPC.
So you can see with just one person accuracy drop, this is the problem.
And on top of this, you are also fetching 20% extra instruction.
You did something which you need to flush again like flush meaning that you actually did not do
anything meaningful over there.
You need to redo it.
So that is wasted effort.
So now, yes, 20% additional instructions, 20% additional instructions.
You know that 20 * 1 sorry 20 * 1 OK, so, so if you since you need to fetch 500 instructions, so
definitely that is 100 cycles you would need to do in the correct path for sure one of the
branches.
We already saw that you know one out of five instructions are branched.
So that means you have in this 500 instructions you have 100 branches, correct?
So out of 100 branches, since you're 99% accuracy, 1 branch went into the wrong path like that it
got predicted wrongly.
So when you predicted wrongly, you do want to keep the pipeline flowing with something, right?
So you kept feeding some instructions in the wrong, wrong direction, right?
So let's say the branch should be taken, but you predicted to be not taken and you kept the pipeline
feeding with some garbage instructions.
I mean garbage meaning that they are not going to be useful in the end when you got to know about
this is going in the wrong path 20 cycles after you start fetching that branch.
So all the work that you did in 20 cycles got wasted and then you again restarted the, you know,
execution on the correct path.
But we fetch 5 at a time.
So of the 20 cycles, we would have fetched 100.
So that's that's the 20% extra instruction.
So now you have actually fetched instead of 500 instructions, you have actually fetched 600
instructions.
So that's what I'm showing over here as a 20% extra instruction.
So what you're saying is why we are not calculating IPCS 600 / 120 because we fetched 600
instruction and then we took 120 cycles.
Is that what you're asking?
I mean the 120 cycles, does that mean we executed 100?
And so, so it took 120 cycles to even fetch 500 instructions?
We resolved the branch at the last cycle of the pipeline 20 cycles.
So that is what Yeah, yeah.
So, so north is meaning that you know from the fetch to execute and then that is what I am writing
over here.
Probably I should not write 20 pipeline stages.
Let us say these are number of stages between the fetch and the execute.
Yes.
Does it make sense now?
Is it clear?
OK any other question?
Yes, if I have five wrong paths, I should still.
Yes, yes.
So you are using 20 cycles, you're wasting 20 cycles.
So you're, you're you're executing in the garbage direction for 20 cycles.
But how much you're fetching in those twenty cycles because you have superscalar?
Yes, exactly.
So in this case, if I have one drop, have two 3-4 or five, it doesn't matter.
I always have yes, no, no, no, no, no, no.
OK, OK, maybe we're going somewhere in the wrong side.
So, So what I'm showing over here is that 20 cycles you, that one single branch that got
mispredicted, it took 20 cycles to get resolved.
So within that 20 cycle, your pipeline is not stalling, right.
So you are feeding something to the pipeline.
So what we feed, we feed actually the wrong things into the pipeline.
So after that 20 cycles, once we get to know that OK, that we made the wrong prediction, we need to
floss the entire pipeline, go to the correct part and start fetching.
So the wasted cycle is 20.
The wasted work is not 20 because now you have 5 wide superscalar.
So wasted work is actually 5 into 20.
Is that making sense?
It's not 500 advances, its wasted work is 5 into 20 because you have 5 wide superscalar.
So if you have 6 white super scaler, your wasted effort is 6 into 20 because at every cycle you are
fetching 6 instructions put together.
Makes sense.
OK so now now hopefully if I go even even more than this would also make you even you know worse
things.
So 90% accuracy.
It's much higher than even making a random guess.
It's nowhere.
Close to when you know, 5050 kind of thing.
So if you go for 90% accuracy, what happens?
So again you need to do 100 cycles to fetch on the correct path.
But now instead of you know spending only one cycle on the wrong path, now you are actually spending
10 cycles on the wrong path.
Then your wasted cycle is 200, right?
So this is you can already see that your the amount of time that you are spending on the correct
path is lower than the amount of time that you are spending on the wrong path.
So you're literally seeing that if you make small adjustment or if your branch rate becomes a
slightly bad, you are actually wasting a lot then we are doing anything meaningful.
So that's what that's what we are showing over here.
100 cycles on the correct path and 200 cycles on the wrong path.
So eventually you took 300 cycles to even fetch only 500 correct instructions and how many
instructions that you have wasted like how many, how much work that you are do did in the wrong
path.
So you wasted, you know, 10 cycles on the wrong path.
So each cycle you have fetched, you know 5.
Sorry.
So you you have wasted 200 cycles on the wrong path because each branch took 1020 cycles to resolve.
So that means you have wasted 200 cycles on the wrong path.
Each cycle you actually fetch 5 instructions together because that's a wide width of the Super
scaler.
So that means you are now actually fetching instead of 100 instructions on the correct path.
You're not only fetching 100 instructions on the correct, but you're also fetching, you know, 200
into 5.
So that means, you know 1000.
Yeah.
So those many instructions on the wrong path also.
So what we are showing over here is then your IPC when you're calculating the IPCIPC meaning that
the amount of work that is in eventually needed which is the 500 instructions.
But instead of fetching this 500 instructions in only 100 cycles, now you have actually taking 300
cycles to fetch.
So that means that your your IPC is dropping to what 1.66?
So you actually started with the IPC of five, you just you know went to 10% accuracy drop and then
you when you're looking at a processor with 1.6 IPC.
So that's what the criticality of the branch breakdown, Yes.
And what's the accuracy part we getting right now in the real world, OK.
Also like is it possible to make programs more predictable?
We are coming to that.
We are coming to that, yes, you can do the maths also with the 60% accuracy.
I mean, it is again like now much better than having just a random guess which is 60%, right.
And if you if you do the same calculation now you're actually dealing with the IPC.
You started with A5 IPC processor and then you are dealing with a fraction IPC now.
So you can easily see like why branch predictor, you know that important like the accuracy of the
branch predictor is that important?
Maybe just to answer your question like the the accuracy that we are, we can extract in real
workloads or real life, you know, scenarios obviously depends on from workload to workload over 95
percent, 99% is not, you know, impossible.
So we can do.
But then there are workloads that, you know, it's very hard to predict.
Like for example, if you do a linked list traversals, right?
So you fetch something and then you go there.
So there is a linked list kind of traversal and then you do the O if my value is this and then I'm
going to do going to fetch the next one.
You have probably written this sort of code.
Yes, good luck with getting a much more IPC over there.
Makes sense.
OK, so so yeah, so so that I'm not going to you know, so this is basically the pictorial view of the
same thing that if if you have the you know, the the the next instruction, if you if you don't have
the branch predictor and then if if you have the branch predictor.
So if you don't have the branch predictor.
So this is what the fetch of each instruction is happening.
So this is the branch which can either be taken to this one or it can go into this.
If you have the branch predictor go going on correctly, then you can, you know, fetch the same
instruction and 12 cycles.
I'm not going to, you know, go too much into detail of this figure, but you can look it offline.
But then if you have a perfect branch predictor that can actually take, let's say, only each cycle.
So it's very important to have branch predictor getting right from the get go.
OK, so I'm not going to animate this, but let's now take a look at what are the different
possibilities that we can do branch prediction mechanism.
So one of the simplest way that you can do branch prediction is basically you always get the next PC
as PC +44.
In this case, we are just considering, let's say your every instruction is 4 byte wide.
So that's why we are saying PC Plus 4.
But consider this that with complex instruction set like X86, that's also even hard to do.
Like PC Plus 4 is not actually PC +4, it's PC Plus instruction size.
And you need to you know, understand what is the instruction size.
So that's a problem.
But for the sake of this discussion, let's consider.
Let's say you know you always get the next PC as APC +4, so always the next.
Sequential instruction is the next instruction to be executed.
This is a form of let's say next fetch address prediction.
And you can think of it as a branch prediction also.
Like you are literally feeding the pipeline with something, not just stalling the pipeline.
So obviously this is definitely, this is not going to, you know, cut the deal.
So we need to make sure that OK, how we can do to make this thing even better.
So one thing that you can do So what exactly this this is doing?
So it's basically saying that, oh, if you have a let's say, if case and then you have a, you know,
some pieces of program that you want to do if the if case is correct.
And otherwise if you you want to do let's say otherwise else case, right?
So if you have the compiler support, so compiler knows, let's say a specific branch that you are
looking at, it's let's say good amount of time it's going to be not taken.
So you can literally reorder the code saying that, oh, if if you know that, OK, your branch
predictor is actually just a next PC, so you're always going to be fall falling back to the next
PC, then you would reorder the code in such a way that your PC Plus four like the fall path.
So this is what we call the falling in a fall back edge.
So you would put the piece of code that is more getting exercised over there and the other piece of
code would be on on the, you know, the other the far end of the jump.
So it's basically what what I'm trying to motivate here is that we can actually layout the program
in the memory space so that if the compiler understands that OK, this, you know, branch is getting
taken frequently, then I would put the taken piece of code on the PC Plus four side.
If the compiler understands that, OK, this piece of code is getting the branch is not taken
frequently, then I would put the not taken path, the code that you actually belong to the not taken
path sequentially consistent like in the in the memory space.
Think of it in the memory space, right?
So you can reorder this program how exactly the program gets stored in the memory space.
S that what we can do to even with this branch prediction mechanism at hardware.
You can rearrange the, you know, software to make this, you know, effective.
So that hopefully answers the question that you are asking, right.
So, so this is what, you know, this paper is a beautiful paper that came up in PLD in 1990.
I mean, as you can see, like these are pretty old, you know, solutions that we have people have
explored.
So this is called profile guided code positioning.
OK, so people have also taken a jab at it in the hardware.
So Intel has implemented something called trace cache.
We're not going to go into too much into detail, but the idea of the trace cache is again the same
thing.
Like if you know that certain part of the branches are let's say more taken, then you would
restructure the code at hardware level so that your, you know, next PC equals PC Plus 4 gets
exercise much more heavily.
OK, Now what else can you do to make it more effective so you can get rid of the control flow
instructions all together.
So how can you do this?
So there are two mechanisms.
I am not going to go too much into details on this.
So, so think of Indiana this way.
So if you have let us say multiple if conditions or if this is so you when you write simulator code,
when you write game simulators like, oh, if this thing, game asset is not initialized, you know,
don't do this.
If this is not true, don't do this.
Like you check all of the conditions and then say that, OK, if any of these conditions are actually
invalid, then you don't initialize the game, let's say for example, or initialize the simulation
environment.
So instead of having multiple of such, you know, predicates and then branching all together, you can
just simply write one big branch saying that OK, if all of the conditions are, you know, either one
of the conditions are true or false, you just going to branch it once.
So that kind of helps.
So combine the predicates and test only once.
So that's, you know, one of the possibility.
The other possibility is you can convert this, you know, data like, sorry, the control flow
dependency to the data flow, data flow problem.
So if you have written codes like some value of the variable is and then if you if you use that
unary operator, so you check something, you know whether it is if?
And then you do something value and then: do something other value.
So that is basically instead of writing if else, you can literally do the same thing with the evils
case, right?
But have you ever wondered like why we do not write in if else case but in a unary operator?
Because the United operator actually converts this if else to a data flow control.
So you're, you're going to compute this thing and put the result in a register.
And that would be you know, so it's instead of causing a if else condition, it would actually 'cause
it a predicate.
So that is what we call it predicate condition.
So it would convert a data flow, sorry, control flow to a data flow.
So I am not getting, you know, too much details of this, but search for this.
So unary operators and an EFL's conditions, even though they do the same thing, they are not
actually treated in the same way in the hardware.
So one is much more beneficial to write over the other.
So these things you can use for maybe yeah, some other cases also.
OK, so, so yeah, we have probably gone through this one.
So we would just go back to this performance analysis and do the yeah, basic understanding a bit
more.
So, so let's say, you know, let's do some sort of understanding.
So, so, so let's say if you if you do a branch prediction, which is always PC +4, right?
So that's the easiest form of branch prediction that you can think of.
So what we are doing So we are saying that OK if wait yes, so OK so this instruction is let's say a
let's say a control flow instructions.
This is a branch instruction and then you decode it and you execute this instruction at this point.
So at any instruction that the instruction that got fetched at T0 you would out know the outcome of
that branch at t = 2 right.
So at this point you would get to know whether you have done the correct thing or not.
So when you would get to know that, OK, you have actually done the wrong thing.
So you have what did you fetch in the pipeline?
You actually fetched APC plus four in this cycle, PC Plus 8IN this cycle.
And then you get to know at this this stage t = 4 that OK, you did something wrong.
So at this you at this stage you would get to know that OK, I instead of actually fetching PC +4 or
PC Plus eight, I should have actually fetched PC Plus, sorry, the target PC.
So whatever you did in these two cycles, that is actually wrong.
So this is what we also, you know, evaluated that if you have let's say you know, the the amount of
cycles between the fetch and the execution is north cycles, then you will literally seeing the
north cycles bubble if you are wrong, right?
So we did this for, you know, evaluation before.
So what you need to do whatever you did in this basically doing it in the wrong path.
So just flush it and then start fetching it on the correct path.
So that's what happens in the pipeline.
Now if I do a simple basic performance analysis, if you think of it in this way, so if if you are
correct guessing, there is no penalty involved whatsoever.
But if you are incorrect guessing, then there is a two cycle bubble.
I mean in this case there is only, you know, 2 cycles between the fetch and the end of the execution
in the ALU stage, right.
So if, if that is the case and consider these sort of assumptions, I mean we are going to do a, some
sort of mental calculation.
There there is no data dependency which solves in the program 20% control flow, 20% instructions are
control flow.
It is you know it is not a bad thing to assume and 70% of the control flow instructions are also
taken then and an 86% of the time you are actually you know correct whatever the prediction is and
remaining 14% of the time you are incorrect.
So what happens in that case?
So your CPI obviously is going to be more than One South.
You would need one cycle to execute like the throughput wise for sure and what exactly you are
getting a penalty for.
So your 20% of the instructions are branches and out of that 20 percent, 70% of the, you know,
control flow instructions are taken.
So taken meaning that you, you would actually have a different target than just PC +4.
So those are the wrong ones.
So what you ended up with so instead of having a one CPI processor, you actually have a you know,
CPI of 1.28 now.
So this is what we are calling the probability of wrong case, meaning number of times you can see
one instruction to be branched and then how many times this is getting, you know, wrongly predicted
because you only have a simplistic naive version of the predictor, which is next, you know, PC +4.
So anything if you, if you can.
So, So what is the, the penalty over here?
So that that's the another mental calculation that you need to do.
So your overall CPI is going to be dominated by the probability of the wrong guess and the penalty
for the wrong guess.
So if you want to design A better processor, ideally you would want both of these matrix to be as
low as possible.
So you would like to decrease the probability of the wrong case as well as you want to decrease the
penalty of the wrong case.
So that's what we are going to look into from the next lecture.
So we would start building from even more sophisticated, but let's say basic version of branch
prediction with a static form of branch prediction.
And then, you know, we would build up to more advanced level of branch prediction, which is, let's
say you know, dynamic level of branch prediction that actually happens in the hardware.
And you would hopefully get to see some sort of the the state-of-the-art in this branch prediction
which people have predominantly used machine learning policies to be specific, like perceptron
learning in actual hardware.
Whatever to make this branch prediction work.
So that's another over area that you can think of as a research problem.
So with that said, so I'll close the session for today here and hope to see you in again in the next
session.
Thank you.